Let's talk about Loaders. Loaders are awesome. They were
introduced in Honeycomb, but are available as part of the
support library. So you can take advantage of them
when supporting earlier platform releases. Loaders are essentially the best
practice implementation for asynchronous data loading within an activity
or fragment. So when you create a Loader, it creates
an async task to load data on the background thread.
It then syncs with the UI thread when the initial
loading is complete, and can be set up to monitor
the underlying data, and deliver any updates to the UI
thread as well. Best still, all that work you did
adding a content provider to your database pays off right
now, with the cursor loader. The cursor loader is an
implementation of the async task loader, specifically designed to query
content providers, and return a cursor, which you can then
bind directly to a UI. It will automatically update that cursor,
whenever the underlying content provider changes, based on changes
to the underlying database. And it will reconnect to the
last returned cursor after being recreated, along with the
host activity, after a configuration change. That means you won't
have to requery data, just because the device was
rotated. So the cursor loader handles all of your cursor
management and background thread creation, UI thread synchronization, and data
source monitoring. If you chose not to use content providers,
you chose poorly. But still, you can take advantage
of loaders, you just need to create your own
loader by extending a think task loader directly. You
can find out more in the instructor notes below.